Guide to the Grandmaster Caz archive, circa 1986-2014.
Grandmaster Caz archive,
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Grandmaster Caz archive, circa 1986-2014.
8109
Grandmaster Caz
circa 7 cubic feet.
Audio Recordings, Memorabilia, Photographs, Printed Materials.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Notebooks, photographs, documents, audio and video recordings, clothing and other artifacts by or relating to Grandmaster Caz and his career as a MC, songwriter, and DJ and his activities as an early innovator and participant in Hip Hop culture. Notebooks contain his handwritten lyrics; cassette tapes contain recordings of his live performances with the Cold Crush Brothers, as well as his appearances on radio shows and other events; photograph albums document his performances and activities with friends & family; Also included are vinyl records and video tapes; a denim jacket with painting by TATS CRU, sneakers, hats, and an action figure of his likeness.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Curtis "Grandmaster Caz" Fisher (aka Casanova Fly), was a member of the early Bronx Hip Hop group The Cold Crush Brothers. He is widely regarded as one of Hip Hop's greatest emcees (rappers). He is currently active as a celebrated NYC Hip Hop landmark tour guide, DJ, and worldwide ambassador of Hip Hop culture.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Notebooks, photographs, documents, audio and video recordings, clothing and other artifacts by or relating to Grandmaster Caz and his career as a MC, songwriter, and DJ and his activities as an early innovator and participant in Hip Hop culture. Notebooks contain his handwritten lyrics; cassette tapes contain recordings of his live performances with the Cold Crush Brothers, as well as his appearances on radio shows and other events; photograph albums document his performances and activities with friends & family; Also included are vinyl records and video tapes; a denim jacket with painting by TATS CRU, sneakers, hats, and an action figure of his likeness.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Grandmaster Caz; Fisher, Curtis.; Brown, Curtis.; Casanova Fly.
Subjects:
Hip-hop.; Hip-hop; Rap (Music).; Rap musicians.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Notebooks and Papers
Series II. Business files
Series III. Events
Series IV. Ephemera
Series V. Media
Series VI. Photographs
Series VII. Separated Materials
CONTAINER LIST
- Notebooks and Papers, 1990-2004
  Primarily contains legal pads and spiral bound notebooks with lyrics and miscellaneous notes.
  - Lyrics, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Lyrics/notes, Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Lyrics/notes, Undated (Box 7)
  - Lyrics/notes, Undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Lyrics/notes, Undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Lyrics, Undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Lyrics, Undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Lyrics, Undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Lyrics/notes, Undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Lyrics/notes, Undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Lyrics/notes, Undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1998-2004 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Lyrics, Undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Lyrics binder, 2000 (Box 15)
    Containers lyrics, a script for Echo Park, and various ephemera.
- Business files, 1992-2007
  Materials documenting Grandmaster Caz's ventures as an MC, label owner, and public persona.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Press kit, clippings, lyrics, 1992-2007 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Calendar, 1999-2006 (Mapcase-folder 6)
    Calendar and day planner filled in with Caz's appointments.
    Restricted to the permission of the curator.
  - Lam Fam Entertainment, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Phone book and day planner, 1999-2000 (Box 17)
  - The MC: Master of Ceremony to Mic Controller, 1999-06-1999-07 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Article written by Grandmaster Caz for the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame and Museum.
  - Jazz Child Records, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Tape Lists, bios, resumes, CEO files, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Hip Hop Declaration of Peace, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Hip Hop Tours, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Coalition for the Empowerment of Hip Hops Old School (C.E.O.), undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Publicity and Advertising, 1995-2013
    - Clippings, 1995-2005 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Clippings, 1999-2008 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Promotional materials, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Contains Grandmaster Caz stickers, advertisements, and business cards.
    - Newspapers, 2003-2013 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Clippings, 2004 (Box 13, Folder 4)
      Clippings previously framed in Caz's apartment.
    - Interview for German newspaper, 2007 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Contracts, Royalties, and Appearances, 1995-2009
    Includes performance, appearance, recording, and distribution contracts
    - Rhyme and Reason, 1995-1997 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Sprite, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Barnard invoice, 1998-04-22 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Television and film appearances, 2000-2007 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Contains contracts, invitations, and proposals.
    - Echo Park: The Hip Hop Musical, 2000-06 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Cold Crush non-disclosure agreement and bio, 2000-09-21 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Contracts, 2001-2008 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Artist Rights Enforcement Corp., 2001-11-02 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Rancore Records settlement, 2002-12-12 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - R.J. Reynolds Tobacco, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Royalties, 2007-2009 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Step Up Productions, 2009-07-12 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Events, 1980-2013
  - Flyers, 1980-1993 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Concerts and parties, 1997-2013 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Concerts and parties, 1997-2013 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Fresh '97, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Conferences and exhibits, 2000-2013 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Event ephemera, 2000-2006 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    Contains VIP passes and ticket stubs
  - Fresh Fest, 2002 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - B Boy Summit X, 2004 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Posters, Undated (Mapcase-folder 5)
  - SUNY Purchase, Undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Awards, 1996-2012
    Programs, promotional materials, invitations, certificates, and ephemera for award ceremonies honoring Grandmaster Caz and/or other hip hop pioneers
    - Hip Hop Hall of Fame and Museum, 1996-2005 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Rock and Roll Hall of Fame exhibit, 1999 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - A Great Day in Harlem '98, 1999-09-01 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Hip Hop Church certificate, 2004 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - VH1 Hip Hop Honors, 2004-2007 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Hip Hop Non Stop certificate, 2004-10-29 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - 100 Handprints in Hip Hop, 2005 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Fresh Five Pioneer Award, 2006 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Bronx Walk of Fame, 2008-04-24 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - The Bronx Ball, 2008-06-21-2009-06-29 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - We Are Family Foundation Gala 2.0, 2012 (Box 9, Folder 19)
- Ephemera, 1979-2013
  - Chic bumper sticker, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Hip Hop Café, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Schomburg Center for Research in Black Culture, 1999-11-08-1999-11-30 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Ephemera, 2000-2008 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Promotional materials, 2000-2013 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    Contains advertisements, stickers, and other promotional materials for various hip hop artists and brands
  - Experience Music Project, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Charlie Ahearn, 2001-04-03 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    Includes treatments for "Wild Child La Rock" and "Mad Monkey Rock"
  - Hands on Atlanta, 2007 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Legends of Rap trading cards, 2007; Basrawi, Claudia; Braun, Florian; Busche, Andreas; Mangold, Cornelius; Krafczyk, Tobias; Superclub Nonbook Publishing (Box 12)
  - Grandmaster Caz action figure, 2011; MU-2473; Starlight Studio (Box 12)
  - Autographs, Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Includes autographs from various artists including Kurtis Blow, RZA, and Body Count
  - Backpack, Undated; MU-2719 (Box 14)
    Leather backpack owned by Caz.
  - Business cards, Undated (Box 5)
    Business cards collected by Caz.
  - Business cards, Undated (Box 6)
  - Grandmaster Caz t-shirt, Undated; MU-2474; Sedgewick and Cedar (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Hats, Undated; MU-2466-2471 (Box 15)
    Contains 6 baseball caps, stored in hat box.
  - Sneakers, Undated; MU-2472 (Box 11)
    1 pair of Jordan Spizike sneakers worn by Caz.
- Media, 1980-2007
  Due to the fragility and potential degradation of moving image and sound recordings, viewing and listening is limited to items that have been digitized. If an item is in another media format, you may request to have the item digitized for access. Information on ordering access copies may be found on the Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections webpage.
  - Sound Recordings, 1986-2006
    - Count Basey, 1986; SR-31449; Grandmaster Caz; Tuff City; 12" vinyl (Box 3)
      TUF 128016
    - The Grandest Of Them All, 1992; SR-31455; Grandmaster Caz; Tuff City; 12" vinyl (Box 3)
      TUF LP 0566
    - Harlem World, Busy Bee, Masterdon, C.C.H., 1993; TR-15903; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Stop What's Goin' On, 1993; SR-31452; New Majority; Elephant Records; 12" vinyl (Box 3)
      ER 103
      Promo copy
    - The Cold Crush live S.O.B.s, 1993-12-29; TR-17094; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Mic check show Hot 97, 1995-11-12; TR-17104; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Grandmaster Caz springtime flava '96, 1996; TR-15877; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Hip hop hall of fame awards Victoria 5 theater '96, 1996; TR-15895; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Mic check show Caz, Creole, Breeze, Mic Magic, 1996-01-08; TR-17097; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Grandmaster Caz spring fling '97, 1997; TR-15899; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Lame fame master mix '97, 1997; TR-15876; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Grandmaster Caz live on Hot 97, 1997-03-05; TR-15905; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Bronx entertainment live, 1997-05-10; TR-15897; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Grandmaster Caz presents Wild Style '98, 1998; TR-15874; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Grandmaster Caz beats for the streets Fall '99, 1999; TR-15884; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Grandmaster Caz dance yo ass off '99, 1999; TR-15879; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Grandmaster Caz R & B flava for my ladies Fall '99, 1999; TR-15883; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Mizza hip hop skit '99, 1999; TR-15875; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Jazz Child Sampler, 2000; tr-17375; Grandmaster Caz; Jazz Child Records; Cassette (Box 4)
      1. M.C.'s Delight 2000, 2. Hate the Game
    - Crown Royal, 2001; CD-4617; Run DMC; Arista; CD (Box 4)
      PRPCD-7434
      Sampler/promo
    - 5 Mics, 2003; SR-31450; Jayquan; Grandmaster Caz; Grandmaster Mele Mel; JAH Music; 12" vinyl (Box 3)
      JM-3002
    - Untitled, 2003; SR-31456; Grandmaster Caz; DJ Signify; Grandgood Records; 7" vinyl (Box 3)
      GG001
    - You Need Stitches: The Tuff City Sessions 1982-1988, 2004; SR-31454; Grandmaster Caz; Ol' Skool Flava; 12" vinyl (Box 3)
      OSF LP 4031
    - Move The Crowd / Scene Of The Rhyme, 2005; SR-31451; Grandmaster Caz; DJ Haitian Star â; 360Â° Records; 12" vinyl (Box 3)
      556.0003.0
    - The Ol' Skool Flava Of... (Rare & Unreleased Old School Hip Hop '86-'87), 2006; SR-31453; Grandmaster Caz; Ol' Skool Flava; 12" vinyl (Box 3)
      OSF LP 4035
    - "Printing H.S." featuring D.J. AJ, Busy Bee, Coldcrush Bros., and Jazzy 5, Undated; TR-17106; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Caz Show Tape, Undated; tr-17376; Grandmaster Caz; Jazz Child Records; DAT tape (Box 4)
    - Caz show tape, Jazz Child Records, Swing Hi, Undated; TR-17093; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Cold crush on Hot 97, Undated; TR-15896; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Grandmaster Caz 1s and 2s mix for car, Undated; TR-15885; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Grandmaster Caz 4th of July jam, Undated; TR-15892; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Grandmaster Caz and Imperial J.C. Live at Bronx Entertainment pt. 1, Undated; TR-15901; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Grandmaster Caz AVS mixes, Undated; TR-15893; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Grandmaster Caz breakbeats volume 3, Undated; TR-15898; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Grandmaster Caz Dredd #1 master, Undated; TR-15912; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Grandmaster Caz independence day, Undated; TR-15902; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Grandmaster Caz interview on 105.9, Undated; TR-17105; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Grandmaster Caz just cuttin!, Undated; TR-15906; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Grandmaster Caz Limelight (live), Undated; TR-15904; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Grandmaster Caz Limelight (live), Undated; TR-17108; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Grandmaster Caz live at Bronx BBQs Djing, Undated; TR-15907; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Grandmaster Caz live at the block expo, Undated; TR-15900; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Grandmaster Caz live at Wetlands, Undated; TR-15909; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Grandmaster Caz old school hip hop volume 1, Undated; TR-17092; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Grandmaster Caz old school R and B, Undated; TR-15881; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Grandmaster Caz old school rap/hip hop, Undated; TR-15882; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Grandmaster Caz presents breakbeats pt. 1, Undated; TR-15889; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Grandmaster Caz presents breakbeats pt. 2, Undated; TR-15887; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Grandmaster Caz presents breakbeats pt. 3, Undated; TR-15888; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Grandmaster Caz presents heaven and hell breaks, Undated; TR-15890; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Grandmaster Caz presents Smoove Groove pt. 2, Undated; TR-15873; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Grandmaster Caz presents the Lam Fam freestyles, Undated; TR-17090; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Grandmaster Caz singles/studio jams, Undated; TR-15908; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Grandmaster Caz Veteran's Day, Undated; TR-17089; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Grandmaster Caz's old school slow jams, Undated; TR-15894; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Kevie Kev birthday jam: the ecstasy garage, Undated; TR-17107; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Mic check show, Undated; TR-17098; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Mic check show, Undated; TR-17101; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Mic check show, Undated; TR-17103; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Mic check show Caz, Creole, Breeze, Undated; TR-17099; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Mic check show Furious Five, Undated; TR-17102; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Mic check show Hot 97, Caz, Creole, Breeze, Undated; TR-17096; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Mizza-Jeep shit-NYC, Undated; TR-15878; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Old school east and west Hot 97, Undated; TR-15911; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Ova 30's grooves: old school rap, Undated; TR-15891; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Parker, Undated; tr-17377; 2" open reel tape (Box 3)
    - Poppa D's pajama party, Grandmaster Caz and DJ Rufus, Undated; TR-15886; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - R and B classics pimped out, they don't make em like they use 2, Undated; TR-15880; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Star and Bucwild morning show, Undated; TR-15910; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - Sway n Tech Int. L.A., Undated; TR-17095; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - The Cold Crush Brothers demos; 1st anniversary Busy Bee, Furious Five, CCYPAL 81, Undated; TR-17100; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
    - The Fun House, Club Negril, Soulsonic, Afrika Bambaataa, Treacherous 3, Undated; TR-17091; Grandmaster Caz; Cassette (Box 16)
  - Video, 1980-2007
    - New York City Hip Hop Convention, 1980-08; V-10990; Ahearn, Charlie; Brathwaite, Fred; Pow Wow Productions; VHS (Box 4)
      15 minutes
    - Old School DJ's - Interviews and Demonstrations - NY, NY, 1999-10-01-1999-10-02; V-10991; VHS (Box 4)
      Reels 14-19
    - Music Videos, 1999-10-02; V-10987; Grandmaster Caz; Parker Lee; Jazz Child Records; VHS (Box 4)
      1) "da grandmasta" 2) "not tonight"
    - DJ Parker Lee Presents: Jazz Child Records - MC Delight (Casanova's Revenge), 2000; V-11000; Grandmaster Caz; Jazz Child Records; Betacam SP (Box 4)
      Side B: Hate da Game - Produced by: da Super Heros (Burk and Parker Lee)
    - Jazz Child Records Video Shoot, 2000-09-23; V-10999; Grandmaster Caz; Jazz Child Records; VHS (Damaged) (Box 4)
    - Rap City: Basement, 2001; V-10989; Cold Crush Brothers; VHS (Box 4)
    - Ay Ay Aya, 2007; DVD-2675; Rakontur; R.J. Reynolds Tobacco Co.; Fort Nails Ent., LLC.; DVD (Box 16)
      Signed by F.I.L.T.H.E.E., Ice-T, and Grandmaster Caz
    - BET Teen Sumitt - Roy Jones vs. Telesco - American History X, Undated; V-10998; VHS (Damaged) (Box 4)
    - Brooklyn Cool J TC, Undated; V-10994; VHS (Box 4)
    - Can't Do Me Nada, Back 2 Da Scene - Studio, Undated; V-10995; Grandmaster Caz; K.G.; Chase; Tone; P-Lee; VHS (Box 4)
    - Good Day NY, Undated; V-10993; VHS (Box 4)
    - Prits Footage, Undated; V-10988; Grandmaster Caz; VHS (Box 4)
    - Recording Session, Undated; V-10992; Jayquan; Grandmaster Caz; VHS (Box 4)
    - Uptown Video, Undated; V-10996; Grandmaster Caz; Rahiem; VHS (Box 4)
    - Yo! MTV Raps - The Last Show (Grant Hill) Liuin Single, Undated; V-10997; VHS (Box 4)
- Photographs, 1998
  - Photo binders, 1998 (Box 15)
    3 binders of photographs
  - Photographs, 1998 (Box 15)
    Various sized photographs of Caz and his associates from throughout his career.
- Separated Materials, 2002
  - Think Again book and CD, 2002; Fresh, Doug E.; Buckingham, Joseph, Jr.; Scholastic Inc.
    Signed by the author